Good morning, 12th day of the עומר. Omer. Also mentioned of course
today is יום השואה, Yom HaShoah, so I hope everybody finds an
appropriate way to be commemorating that. Today's דף daf is דף נ"ה,
Daf Nun-He, 55. We pick up in the middle of נ"ד עמוד
ב. Nun-Dalet Amud Bet. We are dealing with, we have just said
that we rule, we've dealt with these debates about מעשר שני Maaser
Sheni and הקדש Hekdesh and so on and the position, and we
have just said that we rule like רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir by
מעשר שני, Maaser Sheni, that it's ממון גבוה, Mamon Gavoah, and because
we have a סתם משנה Stam Mishna like it, basically a position
of בית הלל Beit Hillel that assumes you don't give the gifts
of the poor, פרט ועוללות Peret u'Olelot from נטע רבעי Neta Reva'i
because that's a type of מעשר שני Maaser Sheni or the same
laws, which shows that it's not really your money, it's God's money,
so you can't marry a woman with it either. So that's we
rule like רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. But by הקדש Hekdesh issues, by
מעילה Me'ilah where רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir has this position that מעילה
Me'ilah by money, by spending money, it does not take place unintentionally
because then you really don't want to do the transaction. So there
we rule the סתם משנה Stam Mishna is רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda.
There are many many משניות Mishnayot in מעילה Me'ilah that show that
when it comes to using הקדש Hekdesh funds, one does transgress מעילה
בשוגג Me'ilah b'Shogeg and one does not do it במזיד. b'Mezid. רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir takes the exact reverse position. One does it במזיד,
b'Mezid, but in general he's prepared to say that there's מעילה במזיד
Me'ilah b'Mezid which is general, which is not the general approach. And
but one does not do it בשוגג b'Shogeg when it comes to
taking possession of funds, spending funds because you wouldn't have wanted to
have done and therefore the transaction is void. So the סתם משנה
Stam Mishna there is against רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, it is like
רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. So now the גמרא Gemara picks up in
the following place. The גמרא Gemara says like this in נ"ד עמוד
ב. Nun-Dalet Amud Bet. The גמרא Gemara says to וכרבי יהודה במעשר
מי לא תנן? u'kh'Rabbi Yehuda b'Maaser mi lo tnan? And I'm sorry,
starting with the words והתנן. v'ha tnan. It's about I don't know,
half of the way down, a little more than half of the
way down, 3/5ths of the way down where there's an asterisk and
it says והתנן. v'ha tnan. But don't we have a משנה? Mishna?
You said we rule like רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that מעשר שני
Maaser Sheni is ממון גבוה Mamon Gavoah because בית הלל Beit Hillel
goes like him, but we have a סתם משנה Stam Mishna like
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that מעשר שני Maaser Sheni is ממון הדיוט,
Mamon Hedyot, it's your money. והתנן, v'ha tnan, we taught in the
משנה, Mishna, הפודה מעשר שני שלו, HaPodeh Maaser Sheni Shelo, if somebody
is redeeming their own מעשר שני, Maaser Sheni, מוסיף עליו חמישיתו, mosif
alav hamishito, you add a fifth, right that's in the תורה, Torah,
then you're going to bring the money to ירושלים. Yerushalayim. בין שלו
בין שניתן לו במתנה, Bein shelo bein shenitan lo b'matanah, whether it's
your crops, your fruit, or whether it was given to you במתנה
b'matanah and now you're going to, you know, somebody gave you מעשר
שני Maaser Sheni and now you want to, and you want to
go ahead and not bring the fruit, but so what you do
is you transfer the money. But listen to what we've just described.
Somebody gave you their מעשר שני, Maaser Sheni, and now you want
to redeem it, it's considered to be your fruit and you have
to add a fifth. Well, how did it become your fruit? Somebody
gave you theirs. It sounds like it was that other person's to
give, right? And that that was like their money that they could
then transfer to you. If somebody could give you theirs and it
becomes yours by מעשר שני, Maaser Sheni, why can't you use it
to marry a woman with it? So the גמרא Gemara says: מני?
mani? Who is this משנה Mishna going like? אלימא Eli'ma רבי מאיר?
Rabbi Meir? ואטו רבי מאיר, v'atu Rabbi Meir, מי מצי יהיב ליה
במתנה? mi matze yahiv lei b'matanah? How can you give it as
a gift to someone else? ואמר מעשר ממון גבוה הוא, V'amar Maaser
Mamon Gavoah hu, it's God's money, meaning because it's your fruit you
might have the right to bring it to ירושלים Yerushalayim and eat
it, but it's not fundamentally your property and therefore obviously you couldn't
give it to someone else. This is an amazing situation where מעשר
שני, Maaser Sheni, we're not in מעילה Me'ilah right now. אלא לאו
רבי יהודה? Ella lav Rebbi Yehudah? It must be רבי יהודה. Rabbi
Yehuda? So you see we have a סתם משנה Stam Mishna that
goes like רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. Your fruit grew, you took מעשר
שני, Maaser Sheni, and
you gave it to somebody else
and now it became theirs. And if you can do that, you
can marry a woman with it. So you've got a סתם משנה
Stam Mishna like רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. So the גמרא Gemara says:
לא, לעולם no, l'olam רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. No, that משנה Mishna
could still be רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. והכא במאי עסקינן, v'hacha b'mai
askinan, דכי יהיב ליה בטבל. k'de'yahiv lei b'tevel. How did the fruit
become someone else's? It wasn't you first took מעשר שני Maaser Sheni
and then gave your friend your מעשר שני. Maaser Sheni. You gave
your friend some of your crop as a gift before you had
taken תרומות ומעשרות. Trumot u'Maasrot. Okay? Here's some of my crop, you
know, I know you need some money, I know you're down on
your luck, here take some of my, some of my crop I
haven't yet been מפריש mafrish תרומות ומעשרות, Trumot u'Maasrot, you can take
care of that, and I give it to you, and you're מפריש
mafrish תרומות ומעשרות, Trumot u'Maasrot, and when you get around to being
מפריש mafrish the מעשר שני, Maaser Sheni, you would give a fifth
if you wanted to redeem it. So in that case I gave
it to you before it was מעשר שני, Maaser Sheni, I gave
it to you when it was טבל. Tevel. גברא חבריה, Gavra chavrei,
you shouldn't be doing that. Okay fine, but yes, but if I'm
giving it to you when it's טבל, Tevel, then טבל Tevel is
still my money. Okay? It's only when it becomes מעשר שני Maaser
Sheni it's not mine.
Now of course
you could say one minute, but if once it becomes מעשר שני
Maaser Sheni it's not yours, then the מעשר שני Maaser Sheni that's
in there already in potentia should also not be yours. So that's
the next point. דכי יהיב ליה בטבל, k'de'yahiv lei b'tevel, וקסבר, v'kasavar,
and this תנא Tanna would be of the position... מתנות שלא הורמו
כמי שהורמו דמיין. matnas shelo hurmu k'mi shehurmu d'mi'an. Before the gifts
of כהונה Kehunah have been taken and before תרומות Trumos and מעשרות
Ma'asros have been taken, it's as if they don't exist. At this
stage, you don't look at this grain that it's חולין chullin with
untaken תרומה Trumah in it and a little and 10% untaken מעשר
Ma'aser and 10% untaken מעשר שני. Maaser Sheni. If you looked at
it that way, then the 10% of untaken מעשר שני Maaser Sheni
wouldn't be yours to give. But if you say, no, no, no,
before it's given it's just טבל. tevel. You can transform the טבל
tevel into תרומה Trumah and transform it into מעשר Ma'aser and מעשר
שני, Maaser Sheni, but right now it's not untaken מעשר שני, Maaser
Sheni, it's just טבל. tevel. So therefore, if it's just טבל tevel
now, then it is totally yours and you can give it to
somebody else. Yes. Why doesn't מעילה meilah apply to מעשר שני Maaser
Sheni because מעילה meilah is only by something that is sanctified to
the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. A קרבן korban is sanctified to the
בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. This has קדושה, kedushah, but the קדושה kedushah
means it's eaten in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, it's eaten by the כהנים, kohanim,
so right, wait, it's striking, it's the same language.
Well, yeah, ממון גבוה, mamon gavoh, so good, right, right, but yeah,
it's a complete, it's a different category.
הקדש hekdesh that we talk about מעילה meilah is בדק הבית bedek
habayis or קרבנות. korbanos. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says so therefore that משנה Mishnah
sounds like it's רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda. but it could work with
רבי מאיר. Rebbi Meir. Okay, תא שמע, ta shma, come in here.
הפודה נטע רבעי שלו, hapodeh neta revai shelo, so we're still going
to try to prove that we've got some סתם משניות stam mishnayos
that go like רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehudah, that say it's ממון הדיוט.
mamon hedyot. Okay, another משנה Mishnah says the following: If you redeem
your נטע רבעי, neta revai, your fourth-year fruit—now remember, your fourth-year fruit
according to בית הלל Beis Hillel has a status like מעשר שני.
Maaser Sheni. And let me tell you a little secret, you can't
have your fourth-year fruit when it's in טבל. tevel. Okay, your fourth-year
fruit, all of the fruit as it's growing immediately has the status
of נטע רבעי, neta revai, right, of מעשר שני. Maaser Sheni. Right,
you understand? It's not טבל tevel that you're מפריש. mafrish. It's everything
that grows in the fourth year of the tree or of the
vine is כרם רבעי kerem revai or נטע רבעי neta revai and
has a status of מעשר שני. Maaser Sheni. So let's see what
the status of this is. הפודה נטע רבעי שלו. hapodeh neta revai
shelo. Do you take תרומות ומעשרות Trumos u'Ma'asros before? What was he
going to say right now? I'm trying to say that you can't
give an answer of טבל tevel about this. Yeah, but then what
do you do then? Let's say I take that, it's still מעשר,
תרומות ומעשרות. Ma'aser, Trumos u'Ma'asros. No. The whole thing goes up?
Well, yeah, I mean except for the פאה pe'ah and the עוללות,
olelos, right?
You have to do this for פאה pe'ah or for בכורים. bikurim.
Right. הפודה נטע רבעי שלו. hapodeh neta revai shelo. Now you are
redeeming your נטע רבעי.
neta revai. מוסיף עליו חמישיתו. mosif alav chamishiso.
You add a fifth and
once again it says, בין משלו, bein mishelo, whether it was your
crop that
grew, בין שניתן לו במתנה, bein shenitan lo b'matanah,
or whether somebody—or not crop, fruit—or whether somebody gave it to you
as a gift. So here somebody gave you a gift their נטע
רבעי, neta revai, you were מפריש, mafrish, okay, but you can't say
it was given as טבל, tevel, it doesn't exist as טבל. tevel.
And nevertheless it becomes yours and you have to add a fifth
because if you פודה podeh somebody else's נטע רבעי neta revai and
כרם רבעי kerem revai you don't add a fifth. So clearly the
point is, somebody gave you נטע רבעי neta revai and now it
became yours. So you see it is something that is owned and
that the ownership can be transferred. So we have another—we have a
סתם משנה stam Mishnah like רבי יהודה. Rebbi Yehudah It sounds like
there are two סתם משניות stam mishnayos like רבי יהודה. Rebbi Yehudah.
So the גמרא Gemara says, מני, Mani, who's this going like? אילימא
רבי מאיר, Ilima Rebbi Meir, if it's רבי מאיר, Rebbi Meir, מי
מצי יהיב ליה? mi matzi yahiv lei? You can't give it to
somebody else. והא גמירי קודש קודש ממעשר, veha gmiri kodesh kodesh m'maaser,
it has a status of מעשר שני Maaser Sheni and if מעשר
שני Maaser Sheni can't be given to somebody else, this also can't
be—I mean you could transfer who's holding on to it, but technically
it doesn't belong to the next person. אלא לאו Ela lav רבי
יהודה? Rebbi Yehudah. It must be רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehudah and you
can't give an answer now that it's טבל tevel because it doesn't
exist as טבל. tevel. So you see that you can take נטע
רבעי, neta revai, transfer owner, and the other person—the next person really
owns it. So we have a סתם משנה stam Mishnah like רבי
יהודה. Rebbi Yehudah. So the גמרא Gemara says, no, לעולם רבי מאיר,
l'olam Rebbi Meir, it could be רבי מאיר, Rebbi Meir, והכא במאי
עסקינן, ve'hacha b'mai askinan, what are we talking about? כגון דיהיב ליה
כשהוא סמדר. kegon d'yahiv lei k'shehu smadar. So it's a similar answer
to the טבל. tevel. The guy gave you his grapes, his מעשר—נטע
רבעי neta revai grapes, or he transferred the ownership of the vines
while the grapes were still like these unripe. Okay, unripe grapes and
therefore because they're unripe they don't yet have a status of נטע
רבעי neta revai or כרם רבעי kerem revai because it's not yet
a פרי. pri. They only get their status once they become a
פרי. pri. So since he transferred it to you before it was
a פרי, pri, he gave it to you before it became כרם
רבעי kerem revai because before it stopped being his money. Okay, ודלא
כרבי יוסי, u'dlo k'Rebbi Yosi, not like רבי יוסי, Rebbi Yosi, דאמר
סמדר אסור מפני שהוא פרי. d'amar smadar assur mipnei shehu pri. רבי
יוסי Rebbi Yosi says that even when something is ערלה, orlah, a
סמדר smadar is indeed the unripe state, it's already considered a פרי.
pri. This wouldn't say that way. And since it wasn't a פרי
pri yet it didn't have a status yet of כרם רבעי, kerem
revai, it was still his and he could transfer it. Of course
the irony is the simple read of those two סתם משניות stam
mishnayos is רבי יהודה. Rebbi Yehudah. But we're saying, no, we've got
a סתם משנה stam Mishnah like רבי מאיר, Rebbi Meir, so we're
going to read those משניות mishnayos also like רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir
rather than saying you have two סתם משניות stam mishnayos that the
פשט pshat is, is רבי יהודה. Rebbi Yehudah. Okay, rather than doing
that we reinterpret both of those משניות. mishnayos. Okay, תא שמע, ta
shma, we're going to try a third time. Okay, another משנה Mishnah
of מעשר שני. Maaser Sheni. משך הימנו מעשר בסלע, mashach heimenu maaser
b'selah, so basically I'm selling Michael there my מעשר Maaser and he
gives me 10 dollars for it, his סלע. selah. Okay, ולא הספיק
v'lo hispik and he did a משיכה, meshichah, okay. but but ולא
הספיק לפדותו עד שעמד בשתים. velo hispik lifstoso ad she-amad bish'tayim. Now
the thing is that he did not get around, so he, he
we agreed he's going to give me ten dollars for it. He
took it, משך, mashach, he drawed into his possession. Okay, but he
has not yet redeemed the value of them until now the, the
price of those fruit has shot up and it's now worth double,
it's now worth twenty dollars. Okay, ולא הספיק לפדותו עד שעמד. velo
hispik lifstoso ad she-amad. Let me see where am I. עד שעמד
בשתים. ad she-amad bish'tayim. נותן סלע ומשתכר. noten sela umistaker. Okay, so
the point is it doesn't matter. He owns it already, because as
we know the way you take possession of cattle is through משיכה.
meshicha. So it's even though he hasn't yet given the money to
לפדות lifdot it, it doesn't matter. He did משיכה, meshicha, he owns
it. And now he can, he does not have to, you know,
pay twenty, he pays ten, right, because it's already his, yes? Don't
we always pay by value not by volume? What? Pay by value
not by volume? What do you mean? Yeah you do, yeah exactly,
you pay by value, you redeem it based on its value. Right?
Not a percentage? Not a- you have your, no you take your-
no no no no no. You take your ten percent based on,
on value, I don't know if it's value or weight actually, I
think it's- I
mean it's volume, פשט pshat is it's volume. Yeah yeah yeah yeah.
No but now that
you have your מעשר maaser and you
redeem it on money, you redeem it based on the value of
the מעשר. maaser. When you're transferring it to money, you're transferring it
based on value.
But now we're devaluating it back to the purchase price.
Not- well that- that is an interesting point that which is correct,
which is, you know, which is and I'm not- I have to
admit I'm not really getting that about this משנה, mishna, which is
is that right now if I have מעשר maaser that I want
to redeem, right, why-
I would have
to- I should logically have to redeem it based on its current
value. So if I went ahead and I bought- took this מעשר
maaser from you, right, and we agreed on
a purchase price, whatever the purchase price is, that's the money that's
going to you.
How much I have to redeem it for if I want to
take the money up to ירושלים, Yerushalayim, that should be based on
its current value. Right. That's correct. That's what I'm trying to figure
out. Let me just see if I can- let me just reread
רש״י. Rashi. Hold on. It's the value you guys set on that
fruit. So that is- Yeah I know but the question is- one
minute. What value is a transaction? It's the price the two people
are willing to pay potentially you could say. Yeah I mean it
sounds like in this- in this issue, it sounds like and I'm
not exactly getting it, that the money I am paying you also
becomes the money on which the מעשר maaser is redeemed, but I'm
not exactly sure why that's true. I mean then you doubly lose
out in the deal. Basically then what you- you know, you
gave away your fruit and you now
have money that you have to bring to ירושלים. Yerushalayim.
I mean I guess you didn't lose out
in the sense that, that
you know that maybe you don't have to add the חומש. chomesh.
Otherwise you would have-
so it seems like what's happening here is I have to- I
have
to relook at this משנה. mishna. But it seems like what's happening
here is that the money I am paying you for the fruit
I'm buying from you becomes the money that is- that- that becomes
the money on which the מעשר maaser is being redeemed. So therefore
if the transaction is that I took it from you and I
did משיכה meshicha and then the price went up, I pay you
based on the original purchase price because that's what we agreed on,
that's when it was settled when I did the משיכה, meshicha, and
then the מעשר maaser gets redeemed on that lower value. Okay. But
why exactly somehow the idea of purchase and פודה podeh is coming
in the same transaction, that seems to be assumed but I have
to look into this a little more. But let's just do the
case one minute. It's his private property. Well that's- no that's what
we're proving. Okay let's- let's read the case again, okay? משך הימנו
מעשר בסלע, Mashach hemenu maaser besela, so- so I was giving- I
was selling Michael this מעשר maaser for ten dollars. Okay and somehow
yes, you're right, the ten dollars he's going to give me is
going to transfer the קדושה kedusha of the מעשר maaser is going
to transfer to it, it's going to be a פדיון. pidyon. ולא
הספיק לפדותו עד שעמד בשתים, Velo hispik lifstoso ad she-amad bish'tayim, but
he didn't give me the money yet because giving me the money
is considered לפדותו, lifstoso, and now it's double the value. Nevertheless נותן
סלע, noten sela, he only gives the original amount
price because when he did
the משיכה, meshicha, that- that finalized the sale and that was the
price we agreed upon. ומשתכר בסלע, umistaker besela, and he profits the
extra ten bucks. Okay, ומעשר שני שלו, umaaser sheni shelo, and he
keeps the מעשר שני, maaser sheni, okay? So he bought it, the
price gets determined based on when he did the משיכה, meshicha, if
the price changed afterwards he doesn't have to give more money, the
sale happened when the sale happened and that transfers the value on
that סלע. sela. Now the problem about all of this is that
it shows that he's selling me his מעשר, maaser, right? So מני,
mani, who's this going like? אילימא רבי מאיר, eilima Rabbi Meir, אמאי
משתכר בסלע? amai mistaker besela? So if it's רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir,
It should not be viewed as as a sale. If it's Rabbi
Meir רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and I'm giving Ma'aser מעשר Ma'aser the
fruit, Michael the fruit, and he's giving me ten dollars, you can't
say, oh, it's a sale and it goes by the laws of
sale and it's determined at the moment of Meshikha משיכה. Meshikha. It's
not mine to sell. What it would be is it would be
just viewed as a pidyon פדיון, pidyon, right? So I gave Michael
fruit and he's agreeing to be podeh פודה podeh that fruit on
some money. That's essentially what it is. It can't be viewed as
of as a sale. If that's true, then the pidyon פדיון pidyon
doesn't take place till the pidyon פדיון pidyon takes place. And when
he gives the money, now it's worth more, he has to be
podeh פודה podeh for more. Okay. Ve'nasan es hakesef vekam lo ונתן
את הכסף וקם לו. Ve'nasan es hakesef vekam lo. By being podeh
פודה, podeh, it's when the money is given, amar Rachmana אמר רחמנא.
amar Rachmana. Okay. Is this clear what's happening? Is everybody clear on
this? Yes? Okay. So here's the here's the Ma'aser Sheni מעשר שני,
Ma'aser Sheni, okay? He gives it, right, Reuven ראובן Reuven gives the
Ma'aser Sheni מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni to Shimon שמעון. Shimon. Okay. To
what? Okay. No, it's Ma'aser מעשר, Ma'aser, well, it's Ma'aser Sheni מעשר
שני. Ma'aser Sheni. Okay. And they agree on they agree on ten
bucks. Okay. And he does Meshikha משיכה. Meshikha. All right. So he
did Meshikha משיכה. Meshikha. He took it under his possession. But he
didn't pay for it yet. All right. And then now the value
shot up to 20 bucks. All right. So if you say it's
a sale, the sale was finalized here, he did Meshikha משיכה, Meshikha,
the sale price was ten dollars. Doesn't matter now if the value's
gone up. He did Meshikha משיכה, Meshikha, he owns it, he owes
him ten dollars. He gives him ten dollars and then the kedusha
קדושה kedusha transfers on those ten dollars. Fundamentally, it's a sale, but
the result of the sale will be that the kedusha קדושה kedusha
of the Ma'aser מעשר Ma'aser will transfer onto the money. Okay. That
is if you think it's fundamentally mammon hedyot ממון הדיוט mammon hedyot
and you can do a transaction with it. But let's say it's
not, it's only mammon gavo'ah ממון גבוה. mammon gavo'ah. Then you then
there's no sale. Doing Meshikha משיכה Meshikha doesn't mean anything. The only
thing that can happen with this is not take possession of it.
The only thing that can happen is an act of pidyon פדיון,
pidyon, right? Everybody with me? So when he did Meshikha משיכה, Meshikha,
that didn't mean anything. The only thing that can be done to
this is pidyon פדיון. pidyon. When does pidyon פדיון pidyon happen? When
you do the money, when you give the money. And when the
money is given, it's already 20 dollars. So you would have to
do 20 dollars because this taking doing Meshikha משיכה Meshikha didn't mean
anything. So the fact that Meshikha משיכה Meshikha means it's his and
all that's left to be done is giving the ten bucks shows
that we're talking about mammon hedyot ממון הדיוט. mammon hedyot. If it
was mammon gavo'ah ממון גבוה, mammon gavo'ah, nothing would happen until the
money was given and until the pidyon פדיון pidyon happened. So it's
another three mishnayos משניות mishnayos now like Rabbi Yehuda רבי יהודה. Rabbi
Yehuda. So amar Rachmana אמר רחמנא, amar Rachmana, ella Rabbi Yehuda אלא
רבי יהודה. ella Rabbi Yehuda. It is Rabbi Yehuda רבי יהודה. Rabbi
Yehuda. So we got three mishnayos משניות mishnayos like Rabbi Yehuda רבי
יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. You can maybe and you've reexplained two of them,
but come on, give me a break. Okay. Why are you saying
that we pasken פסקן pasken like Rabbi Meir רבי מאיר? Rabbi Meir?
Gemara גמרא Gemara said, ella לעולם, ella, ella לעולם ella le'olam Rabbi
Yehuda רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. Fine, says the Gemara גמרא Gemara in
the end. I concede. That mishna משנה mishna is Rabbi Yehuda רבי
יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. Ve'hacha chad stama ve'hacha trei stam והכא חד סתמא
והכא תרי סתמי. ve'hacha chad stama ve'hacha trei stam. So I'm sorry.
Did I skip a line? No. I love that. Okay. Right. The
other two, which we already explained. Fine. We've already explained away two.
I'll concede that this mishna's משנה mishna Rabbi Yehuda רבי יהודה. Rabbi
Yehuda. But now we've got one stam סתם stam mishna משנה mishna
like Rabbi Yehuda רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and two stam mishnayos סתם
משניות stam mishnayos like Rabbi Meir רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. What are
the two stam mishnayos סתם משניות stam mishnayos like Rabbi Meir רבי
מאיר? Rabbi Meir? So one is the mishna משנה mishna about the
mishna משנה mishna where Beis Hillel בית הלל Beis Hillel about Kerem
Reva'i כרם רבעי, Kerem Reva'i, but that mishna משנה mishna of Kerem
Reva'i כרם רבעי Kerem Reva'i is repeated. It appears in Ma'aser Sheni
מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni and it's repeated in Edyos עדיות. Edyos. So
since we've got one mishna משנה mishna that's like that's like Reb
Meir רבי מאיר Reb Meir that gets repeated and we have one
stam סתם stam mishna משנה mishna like Rabbi Yehuda רבי יהודה, Rabbi
Yehuda, we'll go for the two over the one. Okay. Now the
Gemara גמרא Gemara says, ve'isama davka ואי תימא דוקא, ve'isama davka, the
Gemara גמרא Gemara says, look, if the stam סתם stam means something,
if the stam סתם stam voice means that that's how Rebbe is
paskening פסקנינג, paskening, okay, mai lee chad stama mai lee trei stamei
מאי לי חד סתמא מאי לי תרי סתמי? mai lee chad stama
mai lee trei stamei? What difference does it make if it's a
stam סתם stam that's repeated? When did we ever say, oh, because
it's repeated. If the stam סתם stam is meant to communicate that
this is the psak פסק, psak, how can you like it seems
trivial to give more weight to the fact, especially if it's the
same mishna משנה mishna that's just repeated in another place? So the
Gemara גמרא Gemara says no, here's the real point. Amar Rav Nachman
bar Yitzchak אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak
halakha ke'Rabbi Meir הלכה כרבי מאיר. halakha ke'Rabbi Meir. Here the real
reason we rule like Rabbi Meir רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Ho'il ve'isnan
bi'vchirasa kevasei הואיל ותנן בבחירתא כוותיה. Ho'il ve'isnan bi'vchirasa kevasei. Since the
stam סתם stam we have a stam סתם stam mishna משנה mishna
like him in the chosen Masechet מסכת, Masechet, the Masechet מסכת Masechet
the choice Masechet מסכת. Masechet. What is the choice Masechet מסכת? Masechet?
Edyos עדיות. Edyos. Edyos עדיות Edyos which is the Masechet מסכת Masechet
of the testimonies that were given, you know, that is seen to
be like, you know, like very authentic. Thank you. It's a good
for good word. You know, very authentic that comes from early traditions
and therefore the mishnayos משניות mishnayos that appear in Edyos עדיות Edyos
have greater weight, the stam mishna סתם משנה stam mishna than they
do elsewhere. Now, by the way, I just want to point out
a certain delicious irony about this, which is if you read Edyos
עדיות, Edyos, right, Edyos עדיות, Edyos, you know, the Gemara גמרא Gemara
says that how was Edyos עדיות Edyos taught? Edyos עדיות Edyos taught
was, if you remember, there was this whole debate and I'm forgetting
who the protagonists were about whether in the Beis Medrash בית מדרש...
Beis Medrash... If you only allow people that are of the highest
caliber and it's a very and elitist approach, or whether you let
everybody come in and because that will be מרבה תורה. marbeh Torah.
And I forget, I can't remember who it was, but... It was
רבי יהושע Rebbi Yehoshua and רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel was it? Yes.
And רבי יהושע Rebbi Yehoshua and רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel was the
one who brought in a lot of new people into the... and
who, who was it? רבן גמליאל... Rabban Gamliel... they opened up the
doors when who? Who was the populist? רבי יהושע Rebbi Yehoshua was
the populist, right? So anyway, right, so רבי יהושע Rebbi Yehoshua became
the
head and they opened up the ישיבה yeshiva and they
had to add all of
these chairs and whatever and
it says that that's when they taught
מסכת עדיות Masechet Eduyos because
they
let all these people in and a lot of people had testimonies
about תורה Torah that they might not have been תלמידי חכמים. talmidei
chachamim. The מסכת עדיות Masechet Eduyos actually talks about how some weavers
came and gave testimony, but they had authentic traditions. So, and that's
where מסכת עדיות Masechet Eduyos was taught. And what this גמרא, Gemara,
it's not the only גמרא Gemara says, it says this, the weight
of the משניות mishnayos and the teachings in מסכת עדיות Masechet Eduyos
have greater weight than other משניות, mishnayos, even though the whole thing
was gotten because of you opened up the doors and you allowed
a lot of people in that otherwise you wouldn't have let in,
and what they had to say in the end not only is
equivalent weight, actually winds up carrying more weight. So that's why we
פסקן pasken like רבי מאיר, Rebbi Meir, even though it's true of
that there are סתם משניות stam mishnayos like רבי יהודה. Rebbi Yehuda.
If we had to admit it, the other משניות mishnayos where those
were קוועטשעס, kvetches, right, to say it was רבי מאיר, Rebbi Meir,
there are סתם משניות stam mishnayos like רבי יהודה. Rebbi Yehuda. We're
going to take the approach of מעשר שני ממון גבוה Ma'aser Sheini
mamon gavoha because that's what we teach in מסכת עדיות, Masechet Eduyos,
okay, and that's why we rule like רבי מאיר. Rebbi Meir. What?
I just think that that is one of the deepest tensions that
continues throughout all... sure... in other words the populist versus elitist sources
of authority? Absolutely.
It really,
it's
so deep. Yeah, and
to
some degree, right, sure, and of course and to some degree you
could also see it in terms of the issue about the dynamic
in הלכה halacha
between גמרא Gemara and מנהג. minhag. The community does X, but from
the sources it looks
like the הלכה halacha should be Y, right?
How much weight
do you give to communal practice and use that as the lens
through which to interpret the canonical sources, or how much do you
say no, the canonical source is trump? So, there's a lot... yeah,
that's an ongoing tension. If you use a different verb other than
trump... okay, how much they Clinton... yes... you can see this in
non-Jewish works, sometimes Plato was an elitist. Right, well clearly. What a
surprise that the intellectuals were the elitists. Okay. Now we turn officially
to today's דף, daf, and interestingly see this is the problem about
being a little bit behind,
because actually that was the end of
the whole discussion yesterday that סתם stam we פסקן pasken like רבי
מאיר Rebbi Meir by
מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheini and רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda by מעילה, Me'ilah,
and now we actually turn to a new topic. I mean not
totally new,
but it's really detached from our previous discussion. So let's start officially
on today's דף, daf, top of נ"ה. Nun Hey.
תנן, Tnan, actually this will go pretty quick, בלי נדר. bli neder.
תנן התם. Tnan hatam.
Okay, we taught over there in שקלים. Shekalim. בהמה שנמצאת מירושלים למגדל
עדר. behemah shenimtzes miYerushalayim leMigdal Eder. A בהמה behemah was found on
the outside of ירושלים Yerushalayim in the immediate precincts, on the outside
of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, between ירושלים Yerushalayim and מגדל עדר. Migdal Eder. I
do not know exactly how distant מגדל עדר Migdal Eder is, somebody
can go and find out on Wikipedia right now. Not too distant.
Okay, so the immediate outskirts of ירושלים Yerushalayim וכמידתה לכל רוח, u'chemdasah
lechol ruach, and that's that radius around. So within I don't know,
whatever a two kilometer radius, I'm making that up, but you somebody
can go find out. Echo is saying it's fifteen kilometers south of
Jerusalem. Fifteen kilometers. Okay fine. So fifteen... how much is that in...
what is that in miles? Yeah, about ten miles. About ten miles.
Oh, that's a lot then. That's not... that's especially before you had
cars, that's a lot. Okay, so about a ten mile radius around
ירושלים Yerushalayim you find an animal wandering around. זכרים עולות. zcharim olot.
If it's a male animal then you have to assume that it's
A, you assume it came from ירושלים Yerushalayim and B, you're assuming
that all animals that are coming from ירושלים Yerushalayim most likely are
קרבנות, korbanot, which is a little funny thing to assume, but I
guess if the reality is that people did not eat so much
meat in
general and you had tons and tons and tons of animals brought
to ירושלים Yerushalayim for a קרבן, korban, right? So if you see
an animal, and people probably who were raising animals didn't raise them
in the city... Yeah, you went out there for like wool... I
understand, you don't raise your animals in the city, you raise them
out in the fields, right? So therefore the presumption is that animals
coming from ירושלים Yerushalayim are קרבנות. korbanot. Okay, so if it's a
male animal you assume it's an עולה olah because עולות olos can
only be male... only from the right age... we'll get to that.
נקבות זבחי שלמים. nekeivos zivchei shelamim. If it's female, then that can't
be an עולה, olah, זבחי שלמים, zivchei shelamim, so you assume it's
a שלמים. shelamim. So the גמרא Gemara asks first a question, it
interrupts before it gets to its bigger point. אלא זכרים עולות הוא
דהוי זבחי שלמים לא הוי? Ela zcharim olos hu dahavei zivchei shelamim
lo havei? I don't get it says the גמרא. Gemara. If a
male animal, yes can be an עולה, Olah, but just because all
עולות Olos are male doesn't mean all males are עולות, Olos, right?
A שלמים Shelamim
can be male or female. So if it's a male, why aren't
we concerned that it might also be a שלמים? Shelamim? A male
could be an עולה Olah or a שלמים. Shelamim. So אמר רבי
אושעיה, Amar Rabi Oshaya, because the point is is that what what
do you do with it? So we've decided it's probably an עולה.
Olah.
So פירשו, Perusho, presumably it means what
are you going to do? Bring it to the בית המקדש Beit
HaMikdash and bring it as an עולה. Olah. But one minute! If
it's a שלמים, Shelamim, you can't bring a שלמים Shelamim as an
עולה. Olah. So you can't just assume it's an עולה, Olah, maybe
it's a שלמים. Shelamim. Can't bring an עולה-שלמים? No. What? You can't
bring an עולה Olah as a שלמים? Shelamim? Correct. So what are
you supposed to do with it? Why do we say it's an
עולה Olah and what are you supposed to do with it? So
אמר רבי אושעיה, Amar Rabi Oshaya, הכא, Hacha, so רבי אושעיה's Rabi
Oshaya read of this משנה Mishna is going to now be the
focus of our discussion. הכא בבא לחוב בדמיהם עסקינן. Hacha bevah lachov
bidmeihem askinan. What we're dealing with is you, you're a צדיק. Tzaddik.
You found this animal and you want to make sure the right
thing is going to get done with it, and you're willing to
use your own money to ensure that the קדושה Kedusha gets properly
dealt with here. Okay?
And what are you going to do?
והכי קאמר: Ve'hachi ka'amar: חיישינן שמא
עולות.
Chashinan
shema Olos. The male has the possibility of being an עולה. Olah
The female can only be a שלמים. Shelamim? The male can be
an עולה Olah. or שלמים. Shelamim. Great. Okay, it could be one
or the other. Now what are you going to do with that?
רבי מאיר היא דאמר הקדש במזיד מתחלל. Rabbi Meir hi de'amar Hekdesh
bemezid mitchalel. It's רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that says that you can
take something out to חולין Chullin if you do it even willingly
and knowingly. Okay? וקדושה... U-kedusha... okay... במזיד מתחלל. bemezid mitchalel. And therefore
what? So what are you going to do? So רש"י Rashi says
what you're going to do is you're going to take two piles
of money. Okay, this animal's worth $100. So you take two piles,
$100 each, and you say look, if this animal's an עולה, Olah
I'm transferring it to this pile of money. Okay? And then with
this money, the other pile of money will be I'll be מקדיש
Makdish it קדושת שלמים בנדבה. Kedushat Shelamim binidava. If however the animal
is a שלמים, Shelamim. then I'm transferring it to pile of money
B and I'm making pile money of A into an עולה Olah,
like בנדבה. binidava. So at the end of the day, A is...
one pile is an עולה, Olah one pile of money is a
שלמים. Shelamim, Okay? One was because of the קדושה Kedusha that got
transferred, the קדושה Kedusha got transferred to A or to B, and
the other was a קדושה Kedusha that I instilled right now. Right,
is that clear? Okay. So why don't you bring both? What? And
then I bring both. And then I bring $200, I bring two
קרבנות. Korbanot. One will be the transfer, okay, of the... one will
be the transfer of the animal and the other will be my
gift. Which is which I don't know. Now, what happens to the
animal? And the animal, you know, is redeemed. Now here's the problem.
The problem is that the animal presumably has... has no blemish. If
it had no blemish, you wouldn't need רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, you
could obviously redeem it. So just because רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says
there's an idea of מעילה, Me'ilah, which is misuse of הקדש Hekdesh
funds, since when does that transfer into an idea that I can
redeem an animal that doesn't have a...
a קרבן Korban that doesn't have a blemish?
Right, those don't exactly connect, right? מעילה Me'ilah is misuse, stealing, misappropriation,
benefiting. So whatever he says about that, how does that relate to
my ability to redeem an animal without a blemish? Now, I'll get
back to that.
רש"י Rashi maybe thinks
that you can somehow connect them but I want to just tell
you how תוספות Tosafot reads this. Wait for it to have a
blemish? Well, that's what the גמרא's Gemara going to get to, but
I want to tell you how תוספות Tosafot reads this. And this
is like probably the פשט, Pshat, but it's just so shocking you
understand why רש"י Rashi avoided it. תוספות Tosafot says you are such
a צדיק, Tzaddik, you want to figure out what to do with
this animal, what to do with the קדושה. Kedusha. You can't redeem
it because it doesn't have a blemish. So here's what you're going
to do. You're going to steal it. Okay? So therefore, I'm going
to take the animal and I'm going to say I'm going to
take this for myself, but you're doing this because you're trying to
be a צדיק. Tzaddik. Not... okay? And now you took it for
yourself.
What was that act?
That was an act of מעילה. Me'ilah. So what happens with מעילה?
Me'ilah? The קדושה Kedusha goes off. But now the קדושה Kedusha went
off but now הקדש Hekdesh lost out. So what I'm going to
do now is I'm going to bring an עולה Olah, and a
שלמים. Shelamim. In the end הקדש Hekdesh gets... I don't have a
technical obligation, I mean you... what? No, because it's במזיד. bemezid. Okay?
So so therefore, in the end the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash gets
its due because I contribute an עולה Olah and a שלמים, Shelamim.
and I got this קרבן, Korban, I saved us all from having
to worry what to do with this animal because I got it
to go out to חולין. Chullin. I'm such a צדיק. Tzaddik. Okay,
I am willing to risk my own, you know... you know, religious,
you know... חלק בעולם הבא Heilek in Olam Haba in order to
deal with this animal properly. So the גמרא's Gemara of course going
to ask that question in a few minutes. Okay, but anyway, but
that's what it says. So that only works for רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir because I מזיד, mezid, right? And I nevertheless achieved taking this
animal out to חולין. Chullin. Okay, so that's the case for רבי
מאיר היא דאמר הקדש במזיד מתחלל. Rabbi Meir hi de'amar Hekdesh bemezid
mitchalel. And you also understand why it meant הכא בבא לחוב בדמיהם.
hacha bavo lachov bidmeihem. It doesn't say you're coming to redeem them.
You're coming to obligate yourself with that value. I'm going to contribute
an עולה Olah and a שלמים Shelamim, to the בית המקדש. Beit
HaMikdash. And we'll just get this animal out of its predicament by
me stealing it and me doing the evil with this animal. Okay?
So let's take a look. Wait a minute. Okay, fine. Okay. Now
the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, והבמזיד וקדושת הגוף מי מתחלל?
Ve'bimeizid u'kedushas haguf mi mischalel? So the גמרא Gemara says one minute,
if even רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says that you can do מעילה
במזיד, me'ilah bemeizid, he was only talking about something that was owned
by the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash בדק הבית. Bedek Habayis. So let
me just repeat these terms, I've repeated them before but they're important
terms. בדק הבית Bedek Habayis means it's in the בית המקדש's Beis
Hamikdash bank account. You owe, it's funds that they owe and they
can now use it for whatever things, so I can contribute my
car בדק הבית, Bedek Habayis, they own my car, I said owe,
I meant own, they own my car and they can go ahead
and sell my car and use the money and use it to
do whatever they want. That's בדק הבית. Bedek Habayis. בדק הבית Bedek
Habayis is basically it's in their bank account. Okay, קדושת הגוף Kedushas
Haguf means that the thing itself is going to be used. The
classic example of that is a קרבן, korban, but there's another קדושת
הגוף, Kedushas Haguf, the כלי שרת, klei shares, the vessels that are
used, right? Let's say I actually donated a beam because I heard
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash needed a beam to fix a leaky
roof or whatever or they you know or something like that, that
would be קדושת הגוף. Kedushas Haguf. It's the thing itself is being
used, it's קדושת הגוף. Kedushas Haguf. If basically if like I said
before, like a cynic, you know, knows what is it, the you
know, the cost of everything and the value of nothing. So בדק
הבית Bedek Habayis is the cynical approach. The בדק הבית Bedek Habayis
is the only thing is it's dollar value. בדק הבית Bedek Habayis
is just money for the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Okay, קדושת הגוף
Kedushas Haguf is the thing itself is going to be used. Now
the question the גמרא Gemara is asking is, it's very nice that
רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says that you can do מעילה במזיד me'ilah
bemeizid, and the thing will go out to חולין. chullin. Normally we
say it only goes out to חולין chullin בשוגג, b'shogeg, רבי מאיר
Rebbi Meir says it can happen במזיד, b'meizid, that we've seen. But
that's only by בדק הבית. Bedek Habayis. Okay, and that makes a
certain amount of sense. If the only relationship that the בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash has with it is that they own it, so some
act of appropriating it or misbenefiting from it also as a way
of taking it onto myself takes it out of their control. You
know, and you could sort of see I stole it from them
in a certain way and their ownership as a result goes away
and therefore it becomes חולין. chullin. But if the thing is intrinsically
קדוש, kadosh, let's say it's a קרבן. korban. Imagine I sanctified this
sheep as a קרבן korban and then I misuse it, I don't
know, you know, I lean against it, you know, I benefit from
it, okay? Why does it change its basic identity as a קרבן?
korban? So normally, whether בשוגג b'shogeg or במזיד, b'meizid when מעילה me'ila
takes something out לחולין, l'chullin, it's when it's בדק הבית Bedek Habayis
and the relationship of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash to it is
just that it owns it. But when the nature of the thing
is that it has intrinsic קדושה kedusha that defines its nature and
its identity, the fact that I've misappropriated or misused it or tried
to take possession of it is not so obvious, and it's not
just not obvious, the normal assumption is is that it does not
make the קדושה kedusha go away. Yes, Charlie? A first-born donkey has
קדושת הגוף kedushas haguf but it's not going to be used. Yeah,
that's not the same. That I mean it doesn't have קדושת הגוף
kedushas haguf in the same way. Okay, so anyway no so but
I don't want to go there. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
like this: it says okay וקדושת הגוף מי מתחלל? u'kedushas haguf mi
mischalel? So forget במזיד b'meizid, and בשוגג, b'shogeg, since when does קדושת
הגוף kedushas haguf go off because of מעילה? me'ila מתחלל mischallel right
means that the קדושה kedusha you know it gets desacralized. והתנן Ve'hatnan
we taught in a משנה, Mishnah, אין מועל אחר מועל במוקדשים אלא
בבהמה ובכלי שרת בלבד. ein moel achar moel be'mukkdashim ella be'vehema u've'klei
shares bilvad. You cannot do multiple מעילות me'ilas by something sanctified. Why
can't you do a multiple מעילה me'ila on the same object? Why
can't you do a multiple מעילה me'ila? on the same object? Because
it's already יוצא לחולין. yotzei l'chullin. Because once you do it once,
it's already יוצא לחולין. yotzei l'chullin. Okay, wasn't there that old Buddhist
saying you can't cross the same river twice? You know that saying?
Because once you cross it, it's not the same river. And then
apparently the comeback is you can't cross the same river once,
but okay we can figure that out afterwards. Anyway, so you can't
do מעילה me'ila on the same object twice. Once you've done מעילה,
me'ila it stops being קדוש. kadosh. So אין מועל אחר מועל במוקדשים,
ein moel achar moel be'mukkdashim, there's not a מעילה me'ila after מעילה
me'ila, on something sanctified, אלא ella the exception is בבהמה be'vehema which
means a קרבן korban ובכלי שרת בלבד, u've'klei shares bilvad, because a
קרבן korban and the holy vessels have קדושת הגוף. kedushas haguf. So
קדושת הגוף kedushas haguf even after מעילה me'ila do not lose their
קדושה. kedusha. So you can't say with this wandering animal that you
tried to do מעילה me'ila the קדושה kedusha went away. Because with
קדושת הגוף kedushas haguf the קדושה kedusha doesn't go away even with
מעילה. me'ila So let me just finish the משנה, Mishnah, כיצד? keitzad?
היה רוכב על גבי בהמה, haya rocheiv al gabei behema, you're riding
on an animal which turned out to actually be a קרבן, korban,
וחבירו רכב בו, ve'chaveiro rachav bo,
the friend came
and rode on it, וחבירו רכב בו, ve'chaveiro rachav bo, and the
next guy came and rode on it, כולם מעלו, kulam ma'alu, everybody
did מעילה. me'ila It would only be if it's a קרבן, korban,
it's funny because the normal type of animal you ride on is
not a קרבן, korban, but it's not a sheep or a cat,
could be a cow but it's not normal. Anyway, so Anyway, היה
שותה בכוס של זהב, Hayah shoteh bechos shel zahav, you were drinking
in a gold goblet which happened to be a כלי שרת. Kli
sharet. וחבר ושתה בו, vachaveir veshata bo, וחבר ושתה בו, vachaveir veshata
bo, כולם מעלו, kulam ma'alu, everybody did מעילה. me'ila. So the גמרא
Gemara says, so wonderful, according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir you can
do מעילה במזיד, Meila b'Mezid, but since when does מעילה me'ila. remove
the קדושה kedusha from something that has a קדושת הגוף? kedushas haguf?
So the גמרא Gemara says no. האי רבי יהודה היא, Hai Rabbi
Yehuda hi, that's רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. That idea that you can't
remove the קדושת הגוף kedushas haguf from something is רבי יהודה. Rabbi
Yehuda. רבי מאיר... Rabbi Meir... so הא רבי מאיר, ha Rabbi Meir,
the idea that you can remove the קדושת הגוף kedushas haguf even
from something that מעילה me'ilah. can even remove קדושת הגוף kedushas haguf
is רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Now the גמרא Gemara asks the obvious
question. You can't do that. The debate of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
and רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir was only about מזיד meizid and שוגג.
shogeg. Since when, where do you get off thinking that that can
translate into whether the effects of מעילה me'ilah on something with intrinsic
קדושה? kedusha? The גמרא Gemara says one minute, מי רבי יהודה נשמע
לרבי מאיר? mi Rabbi Yehuda nishma le'Rabbi Meir? But we can learn
this idea from רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir,
which is another way of saying there's no basis to say that
this is a point of debate. רב אמר רבי יהודה הקדש בשוגג
מתחלל קדושת הגוף לא מתחלל. Rav amar Rabbi Yehuda hekdesh beshogeg mitchalel
kedushas haguf lo mitchalel. True, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda only says that
the desacralizing happens, the חילול chillul happens בשוגג, beshogeg, not במזיד. b'meizid,
Okay, but he says it doesn't happen with something with intrinsic קדושה.
kedusha. קדושת הגוף Kedushas haguf does not go out לחולין. lechullin. So
לרבי מאיר נמי, le'Rabbi Meir nami, so why should that be different
for רבי מאיר? Rabbi Meir? אף על גב דהקדש במזיד מתחלל. Af
al gav de'hekdesh bemeizid mitchalel. Yes, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says it
can happen even במזיד. b'meizid שקויח. Shkoach. Okay, but this is a
different idea. קדושת הגוף לא מתחלל. Kedushas haguf lo mitchalel. Why should
we assume that he disagrees with this point? He should still say
that whether you do it only בשוגג beshogeg or even במזיד, bemeizid.
if something has intrinsic קדושה, kedusha, that קדושה kedusha cannot be removed.
Or can be removed is if the קדושה kedusha comes only through
the sense of possession and ownership. But if the קדושה kedusha comes
through something that's intrinsically about the object, that it has a—not innate,
I shouldn't say—but you know, a קדושה kedusha that's about its identity,
then that doesn't... then who cares about שוגג shogeg or מזיד? meizid?
How is that relevant? That's a principle that then it does not
go out לחולין lechullin even after מעילה. me'ilah Let's see the גמרא's
Gemara's answer. So the גמרא Gemara says no. It does make a
difference. Why? התם לא קא מכוין לאפוקיה לחולין. Hatam lo ka michaven
la'apukeia lechullin. Yes, if according to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, מעילה me'ilah
only happens בשוגג. beshogeg. So the idea that when you misuse something
even accidentally or only accidentally, according to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, it
goes out לחולין, lechullin, you can understand that actually if I'm only
accidentally misusing it, that's not such a powerful act of appropriation. That's
not such a powerful change of the nature of the object, right?
I wasn't really... so therefore since he only allows it בשוגג, beshogeg,
it's a weaker... meaning the irony is that even when I do
it במזיד bemeizid. it doesn't have an impact. That's true. But the
act of שוגג shogeg is a weaker type of a misuse of
an object and therefore it only works against קדושת דמים. kedushas damim.
It doesn't work against קדושת הגוף, kedushas haguf, against something that in
terms of the קדושה kedusha defines its very identity. But according to
רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, when I'm doing מעילה me'ilah. במזיד, bemeizid, when
I am consciously and actively saying I am trying to remove this
from the בית המקדש's Beit HaMikdash's ownership and take it away from
its identity and take it and my into my possession, that's a
stronger act that even can negate or compromise its קדושת הגוף. kedushas
haguf. Compromise is probably a better word. Okay. הכא קא מכוין לאפוקיה
לחולין. Hacha ka michaven la'apukeia lechullin. You're trying to desacralize it. So
if you're doing it knowingly and trying to desacralize it. Now רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would say that does nothing. But if you're going
to say like רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that it works, once you're
saying it works, according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir it works in
even a stronger way. Okay, so that's why according to רבי מאיר,
Rabbi Meir, he says yes. So here we actually have a nice
development of a concept of רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Besides the absurd
idea that you're going to willingly do מעילה me'ilah in order to
save this animal. Okay, but we have the idea according to רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says there's, you know,
it's all like a גזירת הכתוב gzeirat hakatuv that the things goes
out לחולין lechullin and the תורה Torah only allows it by a
classic מעילה me'ilah of שוגג. shogeg. If it's במזיד bemeizid it has
no effect. But רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says, I think what if
we had not, you know, if we had come to this uninformed
and a priori and I asked you, do you think that it's...
do you think that when you misuse הקדש hekdesh knowingly, you think
it's better or worse? You know, you would say it's worse. Which
one do you think has a more likelihood of changing something's status?
Of course when you do it knowingly, right? And when you're trying
to desacralize and when you're trying to... so that's basically what רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir says. Once you get over the hump that מעילה
me'ilah is only supposed to be בשוגג beshogeg and you allow for
the fact that מעילה me'ilah happens במזיד, bemeizid then you say then
that's actually going to be a stronger form of מעילה. me'ilah And
that's even going to negate its קדושת הגוף. kedushas haguf. Okay, so
that's why this works for רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Yes. So you
mentioned that the קדושת הגוף kedushas haguf can only be by a
being which is actually used in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash or
a קרבן. korban. But let's say a car which... No, only I
commit מעילה me'ilah. *me'ilah*. If it's the car? Yeah. It's because it's
רשות הגזבר *reshus hagizbar*. Right, so I mean I think it's an
interesting question of what, what type of use constitutes קדושת הגוף Kedushas
HaGuf, *kedushas haguf*. If the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash. *Beis Hamikdash* uses
this car, if it's the like the Popemobile, the כהן גדול *Kohen
Gadol* mobile, right? Is that a does any use, is it קדושת
הגוף Kedushas HaGuf. *kedushas haguf*? Does it have to like have a
direct מקדש *mikdash* use? You know what I mean? Not just used
by the activities of the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash. *Beis Hamikdash*, but
like connected to the to the actual structure itself and the, you
know, and the קרבנות *korbanos* itself? So I, I don't know the
exact answer to that. That's a good question. Yeah. Because it has
a stronger impact by being מזיד *meizid*, then should the punishment be
stronger also? Well, yeah, logically, meaning there's no קרבן Korban *korban*, but
there might be, you know, but מלקות *malkos* or whatever, right. I
mean that's a general question even according to רבי יהודה *Rebbi Yehuda*.
Like you're, you know, you're still over on an איסור *issur*, even
though you don't bring a קרבן korban *korban*, right? So it's confusing
by מעילה Meila *me'ilah*, because normally by מעילה Meila *me'ilah*, when we
discuss it, we're not interested in talking about what איסור *issur* you're
over and whether you get punished. The normal focus of the discussion
is bringing a קרבן korban, מעילה Meila. *korban me'ilah* and the object
going out לחולין *lechullin*. And קרבן *korban* is only בשוגג b'Shogeg *be'shogeg*.
And the normal presumption in רבי יהודה *Rebbi Yehuda*'s approach is that
it goes out לחולין *lechullin* only בשוגג *be'shogeg*, right?
So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rebbi Meir* concedes that a קרבן *korban*
is only בשוגג *be'shogeg*, but he says it's going to go out
לחולין *lechullin* even במזיד bemeizid, *be'meizid*. That's רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rebbi
Meir*'s חידוש *chiddush*. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like
this. אימא דשמעת ליה לרבי מאיר בקדשי קדשים *Eima d'shamas lei l'Rebbi
Meir b'kodshei kodashim*. When is that true?
By something that has the highest
level of קדושה Kedusha *kedushah*, meaning it's like
an עולה Olah *olah* or a חטאת Chatas. *chatas*. Okay, בקדשים קלים
מי שמעת ליה *B'kodshim kalim mi shamas lei*? But one of the
cases of our of this משנה Mishnah. *Mishna* about the wandering animal
was that it was a female and it was a שלמים Shelamim
*shelamim*. So here you are, you're trying to be a צדיק Tzadik
*tzaddik* and do מעילה Meila? *me'ilah* with this animal and make it
go out לחולין *lechullin*. So first we had to point out what's
that compromise the קדושת הגוף Kedushas HaGuf *kedushas haguf* according to רבי
מאיר *Rebbi Meir*, and it's able to do that. But how can
it do that by something that has a lower level of קדושה
kedusha *kedushah*?
Now again, intuitively, you should say, wait one minute, if it has
a lower level of קדושה kedusha
*kedushah*, its resistance should be, should be, should be less. But no,
in a way, actually the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s question makes a lot
of sense, right? If something is very, very holy, think about something
very delicate, it can be damaged more easily, right? It's more easy
for some type of a wrong thing to compromise its status. But
if something actually has a lower level of קדושה kedusha *kedushah*, you
might say, you know, it's like then a little misuse, right, doesn't
as much go against its very nature and its very identity because
it wasn't so as holy to begin with. So ironically, and not
so ironically, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is saying actually if it's just
a שלמים Shlamim *shelamim*, maybe then it would not it wouldn't go
out לחולין *lechullin*. Because classic מעילה Meila. *me'ilah*, remember, is by בדק
הבית Bedek HaBayis, *bedek habayis*. And בדק הבית Bedek HaBayis *bedek habayis*
is like קדשי קדשים Kodshei Kodashim *kodshei kodashim*, it's fully owned by
the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*. So now we've said that it also
exists by קדושת הגוף Kedushas HaGuf *kedushas haguf*, but that at least
would be a similar type of a קדושה kedusha *kedushah*, totally, totally
the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*'s. A קרבן *korban*, a beam, a כלי
שרת *klei shares*, a קדשי קדשים Kodshei Kodashim *kodshei kodashim*. But קדשים
קלים Kodashim Kalim, *kodshim kalim*, which to some degree is still mine,
I'm going to eat the meat from it, right? So maybe it's
not so holy that the act of מעילה *me'ilah* would compromise its
קדושה *kedushah* and make it go out לחולין *lechullin*. Okay, so that's
so would you say that? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, אמר
ליה ההוא Amar Layhei Hahu, מרבנן *Amar lei hahu me'rabbanan*, so one
of the rabbis, רבי יעקב שמיה *Rebbi Yaakov shemeih*, רבי יעקב שמה
*Rebbi Yaakov shmeh*, קל וחומר Kal v'Chomer, *kal vachomer*. He says, no,
it's a קל וחומר *kal vachomer*. It's a lower קדושה *kedushah*, it
actually goes away easier, not what I was explaining. קדשי קדשים מתחללים
Kodshei Kodashim Mitchalelim, *Kodshei kodashim mis'chalelin*. If קדשי קדשים *kodshei kodashim* can
go out לחולין *lechullin*, קדשים קלים לא כל שכן Kodashim Kalim lo
kol shekein, *kodshim kalim lo kol shekein*, a lighter thing can certainly
go away. Okay, so I think you I mean maybe that's what
you would naturally have said, but I think you can really appreciate
the presumption of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* that it might be harder
to be compromised if it's not so holy to begin with. In
terms of טומאה *tumah*, the things that are more holy get contract
טומאה *tumah* much more easily. More vulnerable. But the answer is no,
if the קדושה *kedushah* is less weighty, it goes away more easily.
We're not trying to prove anything, we're trying to work out now
that we know this fascinating position of רבי מאיר *Rebbi Meir* that
there's מעילה במזיד *me'ilah be'meizid*, we're exploring it. That's what we're doing.
Not saying we're exploring it. So we've got this funny משנה Mishnah
*Mishna* of a wandering animal and the way one רבי אושעיא Rabbi
Oshaya *Rebbi Oshaya* explained it is you willingly did מעילה *me'ilah*. And
it's according to רבי מאיר *Rebbi Meir*. Well, that allows us to
explore רבי מאיר *Rebbi Meir*'s position of מעילה במזיד *me'ilah be'meizid*. Now
we're finding out that according to that read for רבי מאיר *Rebbi
Meir* that you have מעילה במזיד *me'ilah be'meizid*, it would work even
against something that has קדושת הגוף *kedushas haguf*, would make the קדושה
*kedushah* go off, and even with קדשים קלים Kodashim Kalim. *kodshim kalim*,
it would make the קדושה *kedushah* go off. Those are two things
yeah, it's not a problem but those are two things we usually
never said. We say מעילה *me'ilah* is... Once you're willing to say
it's for מזיד, we open up the possibility that it's by קדושת
הגוף, that it's by קדשים קלים, Kodashim Kalim and that becomes what
רבי אושעיא winds up understanding about this משנה. Mishnah Is it accurate
to say that when מעילה works, that's why it's like a type
of גניבה? Gneiva? Because even a type of גניבה Gneiva is a
possession, right? Yeah, so that's why the בדק הבית, whether מעילה is
fundamentally about misuse and benefiting or whether it's about appropriation and stealing,
to
some degree could be seen as
based on whether we're talking
about בדק הבית or קדושת הגוף. Yeah.
And they used an unusual phrase, אמר ליה ההוא, why don't they
just say? Yeah, אמר רבי יעקב, Amar Rabbi Yaakov, because it means
he was not like one of the, you know, he was normally
more of the anonymous crowd. Like if somebody in a תשובה Teshuvah
writes, you know, one of my students made a point to me,
you know, you might name the student, but nobody else knows who
you're talking about, right? So you want to give acknowledgment, but it's
not like he's a known figure. Okay, now, איתמר נמי, Itmar Nami,
it was also taught: אמר רבי חמא ברבי יעקב אמר רבי יוסי
ברבי חנינא אמר היה רבי מאיר, Amar Rabbi Chama b'Rabbi Yaakov Amar
Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Chanina Amar Hayah Rabbi Meir, רבי מאיר used to
say: הקדש במזיד מתחלל, Hekdesh b'Mezid Mitchalel, הקדש Hekdesh goes out to
חולין Chullin when you do it willingly. בשוגג אין מתחלל, b'Shogeg Ein
Mitchalel, again, if it's a misappropriation of funds as opposed to a
benefiting of it, it does not work בשוגג because then the sale
is void, right? That's everything we've been talking about the last two
days. אחד קדשי קדשים ואחד קדשים קלים, Echad Kodshei Kodashim v'Echad Kodashim
Kalim, and it works on קדושת הגוף and it works whether קדשי
קדשים or קדשים קלים. קל וחומר, קדשי קדשים מתחללים, if the holiest
things can be, קדשים קלים לא כל שכן, how much more so?
So this was development number one. Once רבי מאיר introduces that there's
מעילה
במזיד, then it allows the possibility to say it works against קדושת
הגוף and it's not going to matter קדשי קדשים or קדשים קלים
and that's how to explain this wandering animal.
Now the גמרא Gemara finally asks the obvious question about this צדיק
Tzadik who's doing מעילה. So it says, תמה בה רבי יוחנן, Tamah
Bah Rabbi Yochanan, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan was astounded about this reading.
וכי אומרים לו לאדם עמוד וחטא בשביל שתזכה V'chi omrim lo l'adam
amod v'chata bishvil shetizkeh? Do you tell to a person, 'Oh,
go and sin because that'll make things better in terms
of what we're doing with this animal'? Like, who, since how could
we give license to that? Why would the משנה Mishnah. פסקן pasken
how you're to treat this animal if not trying to tell somebody,
'Well, this is what you're supposed to do'? Is the משנה Mishnah
advocating to somebody to go do מעילה? Okay, so אלא אמר רבי
יוחנן, Ella Amar Rabbi Yochanan, that's not the פשט pshat of the
משנה. Mishnah The פשט pshat of the משנה Mishnah. is like Michael
said. The גמרא Gemara should have just asked Michael in the beginning.
ממתין לו עד שיסתאב. Mamtin lo ad sheyista-eiv. No, חס ושלום, Chas
v'Shalom, you want to know what you think the animal might be,
so that you don't deal with it right away, you wait till
it gets a מום. mum. And once it gets a מום, mum,
then we can redeem it. Okay, so עד שיסתאב וייתי שתי בהמות.
Ad sheyista-eiv v'yeisei shtei behemoth. Now if it's a male, then you're
going to bring two animals, one for an עולה Olah and one
for a שלמים Shlamim, and say, 'If this is an עולה, Olah,
it gets transferred to animal A and I מקדיש makdish animal B
as a שלמים, Shlamim, you know, as a free... as a gift.
And if it's a שלמים, Shlamim, I transfer the קדושה to animal
B and I מקדיש makdish animal A as an עולה Olah as
a gift.' Okay, but you wait till it gets a blemish. Nobody's
doing any מעילה. You just wait till it gets a blemish. Doesn't
it cost twice as much or just say the value of this
animal now it could be redeemed and then I split the money
between עולה...? Olah...? No, because then you're misusing half the money. In
the end, if you're... you are being the צדיק Tzadik because in
the end if you're dealing with it, you're using two of your
animals to bring as a קרבן to deal with this one animal.
So you are being a צדיק here, but you're not being a
רשע rasha at the same time, okay? You're waiting till it gets
a blemish and because you don't know, a female could only be
a שלמים, Shlamim, so you only need to transfer, so you can
actually bring the animal directly if it's a female. You don't even
have to redeem it. But a male that's either an עולה Olah
or a שלמים, Shlamim, you wait till it gets a מום mum
and you get two animals and one of them is a substitute
and one of them is your gift. Again, this only be found
at the right age, right? Well, the גמרא Gemara is going to
get to that. Okay, so now I think we can actually finish
the דף daf if there's no questions because you'll see it'll go
very fast. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: okay, אלא אמר
רבי יוחנן ממתין לו עד שיסתאב וייתי שתי בהמות ומתנה. Ella Amar
Rabbi Yochanan mamtin lo ad sheyista-eiv v'yeisei shtei behemoth u-matneh. You bring
two animals and you make the stipulation like I just explained. אמר
מר, Amar Mar, so now let's analyze this. זכר עולה, Zachar Olah,
if it's a male we're treating it, it could be an עולה.
Olah. Okay, it could be an עולה, Olah, it could be a
שלמים, Shlamim? so you need two animals. So the גמרא Gemara says,
one minute, why only two? דילמא תודה היא Dilma Todah hee? Maybe
it's a תודה Todah and not a שלמים? Shlamim.
Okay, a תודה Todah is sort of like a subset of a
שלמים. Shlamim All right, דמייתי נמי תודה, d'meisei nami Todah, fine, bring
three animals.
Okay, והא בעיא לחם v'ha ba-ya lechem? One minute, if it's a
תודה, Todah, you don't just bring an animal, the animal has to
come with its loaves of bread. Okay, דמייתי נמי לחם, d'meisei nami
lechem, you bring the bread. And again, so either if it wasn't
a תודה, Todah, then you were מקדיש makdish the animal and the
bread as your נדבה, nedavah, as your, you know, your gift. Okay,
and if it was a תודה, Todah, you transferred and you were
מקדיש makdish the other two, the שלמים shlamim, and the... and the
עולה. Olah. So you have all three possibilities, one of them is
the transfer and the other two are your gift. Okay, ודילמא אשם
הוא v'dilma asham hu?
Now maybe it's an אשם asham and that's a
real problem because an אשם asham you can't do as a free
will. An אשם asham can be a male and it can't be
free will. So how you going to deal with the possibility that
it might be an אשם? Asham? So the גמרא Gemara says no,
אשם בן שתי שנים, Asham ben shtei shanim, now we get to
the issue of age, an אשם Asham has to be a two-year
animal and the case in the משנה Mishnah. is that it was
a one-year animal, so that rules out the possibility it's an אשם.
Asham. ודילמא אשם מצורע הוא אשם נזיר הוא? v'dilma asham metzora hu
asham nazir hu? Maybe it's an אשם Asham of a מצורע metzora
or אשם asham of a נזיר nazir which was a one-year-old animal?
גמרא Gemara says no, לא שכיח, lo shchiach, that's not so common,
we don't have to worry about that. ודילמא פסח הוא? v'dilma pesach
hu? Maybe it's a פסח pesach and a פסח pesach was one
year old and male, so why don't we have to worry about
that? So the גמרא Gemara says look, פסח בזמנו, pesach bizmano, if
it's right around יום טוב, Yom Tov, מיזהר זהירי בי, miz'harei hiri
bei, people are careful, you don't have to be concerned that this
is a פסח pesach wandering around. ושלא בזמנו, v'shelo bizmano, and if
it's after פסח, pesach, so שלמים הוא. shlamim hu. What's the status
of a פסח pesach once it's no longer פסח? pesach? It's a
שלמים, shlamim so שלמים Shlamim, we've already got covered. Okay. ודילמא בכור
ומעשר נינהו? v'dilma bechor u'maaser ninhu? Ah, here's another animal that could
be one year and male. It could be a בכור bechor or
מעשר. maaser. How you dealing with that possibility? So the גמרא Gemara...
says no, גמי הלכתא, g'mai hilchasa, what's the status of a בכור
ומעשר? bechor maaser? למיכלינהו במומן. l'michli'inhu b'muman. You know what happens to
a בכור ומעשר? bechor maaser? Once it gets a blemish, the irony
is it's the one קרבן that it has a קדושה of a
קרבן, but if it gets a blemish you don't have to do
anything. You can eat it outside the בית המקדש. So בכור bechor
and מעשר, maaser, if it gets a blemish, the owners can eat
it outside the בית המקדש. So you know what? That's exactly what
you're doing. You're waiting till the animal gets a blemish, you're redeeming
it on these three possibilities: עולה, Olah, שלמים, shlamim, תודה. Toda. And
what you going to do with the original animal? You're going to
eat it. So that's what you would do if it was a
בכור bechor or מעשר. maaser. Okay, הכא נמי במומן מיתכלי. hacha nami
b'muman mi'achli. Okay, great. We solved that משנה. Mishnah It says it's
an עולה Olah but what it really means is you bring three
animals. All right, now we're going to get to the second part...
No, the owners... Now we're going to do the second part of
the משנה. Mishnah אמר מר, Amar mar, נקבה זבחי שלמים, nekeiva zivchei
shlamim, if it's a female then you don't have to worry about
other types of things, it could only be a שלמים, shlamim. bring
it as a שלמים. shlamim We got a little bit of a
problem. דילמא תודה היא? dilma toda hi? But it could also be
a תודה, Toda, right? And a תודה Toda also could be a
female. Okay, דמייתי תודה, d'maisi toda, so yes, that's true. Just bring
a שלמים shlamim? though, so just bring it. So תוספות Tosafot asks
that, why don't you just be... yeah, so that might be a
problem, but can you be מקדיש makdish לחם lechem בתנאי bitnai and
whatever and can you be מייבי קדשים לבית הפסול? meivi kodshim l'beit
hapsul? תוספות Tosafot deals with that, like why couldn't you have one
animal do double duty? But let's... you can look at תוספות. Tosafot.
Anyway, maybe it's a תודה, Toda, so how can you just assume
it's a שלמים? shlamim? Fine, you bring another animal so you cover
your bases there. Okay, דמייתי תודה ואבינא לה לחם, d'maisi toda v'avinan
leh lechem, oh, but if it's a תודה Toda you need bread.
Fine, דמייתי נמי לחם, d'maisi nami lechem, you bring that, you got
your bases covered. ודילמא חטאת היא? v'dilma chatas hi? Maybe it's a
חטאת. Chatas And now we've got the same problem as we had
before, that a חטאת Chatas could be female, but a חטאת Chatas
cannot be brought as a נדבה, nedavah, free will. So if it's
not a חטאת Chatas. I'm going to bring this animal as a
חטאת. Chatas? You're stuck. What you going to do if it's a
חטאת? Chatas So the גמרא Gemara says oh, חטאת בת שנתה, chatas
bas shnata, a חטאת Chatas has to be a one-year-old animal, ואשתכח
בת שתי שנים, v'ishtakach bas shtei shanim, and we're talking
that it's two years old. Well let's say I don't know, so
that's what the גמרא is going to ask. And of course the
irony now is that we're saying the beginning of the משנה Mishnah.
is talking only about a one-year-old animal and the end of the
משנה where it talks about a female is talking only about a
two-year-old animal. I mean, it's a complete re-read of the whole משנה.
All right, anyway, moving on. ודילמא חטאת שעברה שנתה? v'dilma chatas she'avrah
shnata? Maybe it was a חטאת Chatas? and it's been wandering around
for a while, right, or it's more than a year old? So
maybe it's still a חטאת? Chatas? No, לא שכיח, lo shchiach, that's
not so common that it would, you know, if it's... it's going
to get... you know, it would not have been wandering around that
long or if it would have been brought already, whatever, that doesn't
happen so much. Okay, לא שכיח. lo shchiach. אשתכח בת שנתה מאי?
Ishtakach bas shnata mai? So now the גמרא says what is it
if it's a one-year-old animal? If you find a one-year-old female animal
running around, what are you supposed to do? Maybe it's a חטאת?
Chatas, Exactly. So גמרא says, תניא, tanya, we found a ברייתא, braitah,
חנניה בן חכינאי אומר, Chananya ben Chachinai omer, עז בת שנתה לחטאת,
ez bas shnata l'chatas, that's the פסוק. pasuk. Okay, a goat of
one year for a חטאת, Chatas which means if it because it
could be a חטאת Chatas. you've got to bring it as a
חטאת. Chatas So the גמרא... you can't do anything, I mean a
חטאת Chatas. can only be brought as a חטאת. Chatas, So you
can't do a free will. So the גמרא says, וחטאת סלקא דעתך?
v'chatas salka daatach? What do you mean? But maybe it's not a
חטאת, Chatas. right? Maybe it's a what do you call it, you
know, maybe it's a שלמים? shlamim That doesn't give an answer. אלא
אמר אביי, Ella amar Abaye, כחטאת. k'chatas. No, it means you have
no choice but to treat it as a חטאת. Chatas, Which means
what? כונסה לכיפה והיא מתה מאליה. Konas'la l'chippa v'hi mesa mei'aleha. You
put it in a cell and you let it die. And then
you bring... you don't bring anything. Because you wanted to do something
with this... So I guess you could say if it has קדושה
שלמים shlamim I'm transferring the קדושה and I'll bring this animal as
a שלמים shlamim and regardless I'm now going to let the animal
be sit in a cell and wait for it to die. Right,
that's and that's what you'd have to do because it might be
חטאת, so in terms of an עולה Olah and a תודה Toda
and you let the animal die. Right, I mean it's funny, once
you're letting the animal die, maybe you just let the animal die.
But I guess you're right, like if it has קדושה and it's
a שלמים and I can deal with it, why should I let
it die? So right, so maybe you'd have to do both. Okay,
look at that, we got
all caught
up
and we
actually ended
a
minute early.
Okay.